hey folks welcome to Bret Weinstein's
Dark Horse podcasts I am sitting here
today with Chloe Valerie who is the
architect behind theory of Enchantment
welcome Chloe thank you can you tell me
before we get into any of the other
things that we want to discuss what the
theory of Enchantment is so theory of
Enchantment is a curriculum that I
designed to teach mental health and
healthy identity formation but the
uniqueness of the curriculum is that it
uses pop culture to teach these things
so when you say identity that's
obviously a charged term these days
you're talking about racial gender
you're talking about these things or do
you mean something else by no I think I
mean something actually quite deeper
than that which is sort of like the
fundamental humanists that we think of
when we think of individuals and so it's
something that transcends all the
categories that you just mentioned in
some way so it almost sounds like an
alternative to this modern view of
identity maybe I think I think that you
know I don't think that race or gender
or such categories can't also be
discussed I think that this just
provides us with a better framework or a
better roadmap to point us in the right
direction as we discuss those things
cool so maybe let's be bold okay and
actually maybe I have to ask your
permission to do this first okay there's
a way in which you as a person of
African descent are living in a world in
which race is playing such a prominent
role that whether you want that to be an
important part of the way you're
interacting it is on so many people's
minds that you're dragged into a lot of
conversations about it and there's
certainly a part of me that would love
to just bypass it entirely okay and then
there's another part of me that thinks
actually this is an opportunity sure you
and I I think it's fair to say our
friends yeah and I feel very comfortable
with you I think you feel comfortable
with me certain that means that in a
sense we're really well positioned to
have a conversation about things that
other people aren't sure what to do with
okay
so can you tell me a little bit about
your background and then what you see on
the modern landscape with respect to
this topic that has become so charged
sure that's a big question
Kosmic even so I'm from New Orleans
Louisiana I'm african-american both my
parents are black my grandparents are on
both my parents side are black I'm
fairly certain that my parents ancestors
or at least by I think my parents
ancestors who were slaves or probably
slaves in Shreveport because Shreveport
Louisiana because I have a lot of
friends family that still lives in
Shreveport Louisiana but also I think my
father's side of the family goes back to
Haiti and that's the extent to which I
know really about sort of immediate
regional places that my family has come
from so when you say goes back to Haiti
your father's family you believe was
living in Haiti so I believed in Haiti
pressing sell farming sugar or something
along those line I don't know I don't
know the specifics of that but I think
that they I think that that was the
particular place where they were most
recently before coming to America got it
that make sense any idea what part of
Africa your family emerges from so West
Africa but that actually doesn't really
tell us anything because West Africa was
we're like the slave port was yeah so
everyone was going through West Africa
but I mean maybe it tells us something
if it says like 80 percent from West
West Africa maybe that means something
I'm not sure but my sense is that it's
hard to tell
so Louisiana that's interesting yeah you
were in Louisiana in New Orleans during
Katrina yes I was 11 years old or 11
years old yeah all right
we had to leave for a year because the
city shut down you know there was for a
host of reasons off obviously the
flooding and the shutting down of the
city as well but thankfully my parents
house was not destroyed
and so we were able to go back after a
year but I was still gone all for all of
eleven and so your family was there you
were in yeah in Louisiana for the
hurricane yeah and so you saw you saw in
person what most of us saw on television
well yes or no so I didn't see a lot of
the more harrowing images that people
saw on television just because so my
grandmother was working at the VA
hospital at the time and we were housed
there for about a week and then
everything just became unbearable
because like like I said the city was
shut down so we got rescued on military
trucks and they took us to Zephyr
Stadium and then from there they took us
on buses where we went to Alexandria
Louisiana where I stayed for a year so I
saw I mean it was kind of weird to be on
a military truck for example and hear
gunshots in the distance but I also
think that because I was 11 I don't
really remember a lot of it it's it's
honestly a blur to a certain extent but
I do i do remember like some things
obviously being out of the ordinary but
it wasn't as howling as other images of
like yeah people stranded out and people
in the Superdome and sort of the
troubles that they had as well people
dead in their wheelchairs exactly
exactly yeah yeah it was quite dramatic
on the outside yeah of course you were
11 right so there's also the added fact
of having seen it through the eyes of a
kid yeah at that point yeah I must tell
you I have a very clear visceral memory
of house Katrina unfolded
I was watching news coverage like
everybody else and I remember there was
a moment I think it was George Bush
himself who was announcing that the
federal government was doing all it
could but that it was having trouble
getting its trucks into the city to help
people and I had this visceral reaction
I was overwhelmed with anger because
there's no
way even if the president had forgotten
that the federal government had
helicopters right the federal government
knew that it had them right and so the
fact that it was going to pretend that
it couldn't help people because the
roads were in bad condition it was
clearly an excuse sure so you know that
actually in in light of what you do with
theory of Enchantment using pop culture
it it is the first place that I became
aware of Kanye West well famous yeah but
legend exertion was that yeah George
Bush did not care about black people
yeah I have to say I don't think was
exactly what was going on right but I
did understand exactly why that was the
impression because whatever it was that
he did and didn't care about somehow
helicopters that absolutely needed to
arrive with help immediately were not
arriving and so there was some failure
of empathy on a massive scale
definitely but anyway it's it's it's
actually kind of a I think it's a a
national trauma that we all witnessed
the failure of of our government at that
moment that's so interesting it's
interesting to be to have lived that as
opposed to have been the viewer of that
and I wonder like the relationship that
creates between the thing that is
happening and the thing the person
that's happening to because yeah I don't
know maybe again because I was 11 and
because I was in the middle of it as
opposed to observing it that that it's
scope at that point in time was lost on
me because I was in the middle of it as
opposed to observing it yeah it's
impossible to understand the magnitude
of the context if you're in it and yeah
that's compounded by being a child yeah
at that point my sense at the time
trying to understand what it was that
had gone wrong and I have no idea
whether I'm right about this or another
but I have the sense that there was a
campaign I mean effectively we know
there was a campaign and it came from
the right okay and that campaign was
effectively designed to wean us off
dependence on government at the
antipathy for government on the right
was so great
that it essentially took that part of
government which functioned and hobbled
it so that we wouldn't get the sense
that government was the solution to any
problem I see and you know on the Left I
would say there is an over-dependence on
governmental solutions often that have
unintended consequences so it's not like
I'm saying the only fault here is on the
right but the the hobbling of the
government was in full swing at the
point Katrina hit I mean it was almost
at completion ok and I had the sense
that there was a desire not to have
helicopters fly in and save the day
because it would remind people that
government actually stands between us
and chaos and that it is necessary and
useful and you well that's interesting
cuz that brings up a contradiction of
the right as you're saying that the last
part the last piece that you just said
because presumably the right believes in
yes they believe in small government but
they also believe in the governing of
the self in order to thwart chaos but
it's interesting that that doesn't
extend from the individual to the
collective in the right wing's conscious
sense of sense of you know consciousness
or whatever however you want to describe
it because consistency would suggest
that if you believe that self government
is necessary to fort or to keep chaos
back then if you were to take that and
apply it on a macro level then
governments are necessary also to thwart
chaos right interesting
and so that's an inherent sort of
inconsistency now when you say although
I could probably still mend the response
to that but yeah well I mean all of
these things will be yeah a balance and
sure any of them can be taken too far
better when you say the governance of
self yeah are you talking about
basically self-restraint well I just
know that the right tends to talk about
the importance of like you know self
regulation and not making sure not to be
you know swept up by the passion
that's that's a that's definitely mostly
right-wing talk
and so by self-governance I just mean
being in control of one's faculty so as
to not descend into chaos whether that
chaos is decadence whether that chaos is
in excess of anything right basically to
always be in moderation and but in being
in moderation requires governance yeah
and so if you don't extend that from the
micro to the macro then you could it's
it begs a question at the very least
yeah and you know I think wise people on
the left and right can surely agree that
it is important essentially to
self-police at some great well now we we
on the left might disagree with us on
the right I don't mean to include you
one way or the other you define yourself
as you will sir we on the left meaning
me and on the left might have a
different view of where the the border
of that responsibility is I think we
could all agree that it is essential and
in fact one of the things that I am most
disturbed by that I see on the modern
radical left is essentially a juvenile
abdication of responsibility to
self-regulate a desire you know a sort
of recognition I want that thing and
therefore I am entitled to it rather
than any notion that there are
trade-offs and balances that have to be
struck and feeding values and these
sorts of things but anyway I would love
for the left and right to recognize the
part of this viewpoint that they
actually do share right unfortunately I
think that would require giving up
previously held positions the other is a
monster so you cannot find something of
quality in a monster and even more so
you cannot admit that you find something
in a monster which is similar to you
because now you are identified with the
monster so forever yeah 15 years I have
saying the following set of ideas the
Fox News viewer believed that the New
York Times reader is insane
the New York Times reader believes yes
the Fox News viewer is crazy they're
both right yes okay yes and yes there's
something very powerful in what you said
about it is impossible to find that
point of agreement in the monster on the
other side what I have trouble relating
to because frankly I don't see a monster
on the other side generally I
occasionally see them all those people
exist but they're not common sure right
it's not like there's an entire right
movement you know it's not like half the
population is right awful that's right
true so I have no trouble sitting with
people who I'm told I shouldn't be able
to get along with sure right I'm told
that I shouldn't be able to get along
with creationists for example I don't
find that sitting at the table with them
is that way I don't know find myself
persuaded sure but it's not hard sure to
grant them the benefit of the doubt and
to discover their humanity I don't find
this problem with people on the right
generally even though I'm far from the
right mm-hmm I don't get the sense that
you have trouble seeing humanity on the
other side in fact your whole dear even
Chapman ciriculum is built around the
idea of really deeply understanding the
humanity on the other side yes so if you
and I find this relatively easy to look
across the aisle at people we're
supposed to not be able to fathom and to
actually find their humanity is there
something a is it much easier than
people think is there just like a simple
error that they're making or is it
harder mm-hmm then you and I find it
because there's something about other
people that stands in their way that
just doesn't happen to be part of either
of us I actually think it is hard in
general because of what it requires one
too it requires one too like shed
preconceived notions and if one
if one's identity is attached to
preconceived ideas then and if you have
to shed it then it's sort of like feels
it feels like a disaster you know if you
identified with a certain set of beliefs
that said you have to bash person X
because they they have a different set
of opinions than you and you heavily
identify with it like that wasn't just
an opinion you had it was a part of who
you are or who you conceived yourself to
be and now all of a sudden we're saying
actually you can find common ground and
you can find you can even find affinity
for this person that is a total
rejection of the thing that you thought
was fundamentally a part of your very
being and that's hard to actually
overcome like living through that
wrestling with that and accepting that
so I want to know are you saying you
find it hard or you saying that your
experience with other people tells you
that it's hard I'm saying I don't find
it hard anymore but I used to find it
hard and so I can understand how on a
psychological level it could be hard
okay and do you know what experience you
had or what you realized that caused it
to become easier oh to become easier
that's interesting question I don't know
if it was I don't know if I could
pinpoint it to a very specific thing or
moment I think it was a gradual well
actually it entailed reading a couple of
books honestly so East of Eden was
probably one of the most important books
I read in my 20s actually that like
enabled me to do that and to think in
this way so to speak but other than that
I think it was just an organic process
of wrestling with these ideas which
doesn't sound very satisfying but no
first of all I don't I don't he'd be
wonderful if there was a simple answer
yeah there was a simple answer it would
probably be more widely discussed okay
oh who knows but actually yeah so I
think I think the answer might be that I
discovered that what we're talking about
the ability to sit across from someone
who you don't like or whose ideas you
don't like and still find affinity for
them that ideas actually found
I would argue we actually do believe in
that and and the proof that we believe
in that is its present in pop culture so
like the movies that we love the Disney
movies that we love for example is are
often all about that right and they
repeat themselves in Disney movies a lot
of the artists songs that we listen to
I'm saying like a big cross-section of
society right the types of artists that
we gravitate toward oftentimes do talk
about empathy in their music or do not
even talk about it but but implicitly
it's there essentially and so I think it
was a realization that it is deeply
embedded in what we desire to want to do
at the very least because it's found in
the pop culture that would create and so
this idea that I initially thought was
like a foreign idea became common in my
eyes and I think that that realization
and that organic sort of unfolding of
the discovery of the meaning at the
bottom of pop culture helped me to be
able to more easily do that because then
that that means that what we're
describing is the fabric of stories
found through art and so then it becomes
then I have an entirely new relationship
with that entire concept an entire
process I really like that and I realize
in hearing you describe it there are two
things in my experience that dovetail
with what you're saying
one is I have a memory when I was I
don't know how young I would have been
maybe eight or nine all right and I
think I was you know ranting about the
injustice of what was happening to
nature okay I've always had a very
strong okay affinity for nature and a
fascination with it and I've always had
a desire to like animals a lot and I
like thinking about them and watching
them and anyway I was ranting about
maybe I was ranting about hunting okay
and Erik you know three and a half years
older than me mm-hmm
said you know
you really need to read field and stream
okay all right and I said what are you
talking about and he said you really
need to understand what it is on the
other side you need to understand how
they see the world and you know it's a
little hard to admit how profound and
impact that had on my life because at
some level I now recognize myself as a
50 year old adult who delights in being
able to cross unbridgeable
gaps all right it's like you know
there's a way I think it's very
honorable work and I don't mm-hmm in any
way feel cynical about it but there's a
way in which it does strike me as a
challenge when I hear there's a gap I'm
not supposed to be able to cross I
always want to figure out whether I can
convey something to the person on the
other side sure about my humanity that
will cause them to suddenly wake up vice
versa the other thing though is I'm
watching a world develop online that
obviously didn't exist sure I was a
young person you know you're you're
young enough that it has existed for
most of your adult life or maybe all of
your adult life but I'm watching
something happen with for example the
videos that people post of their pets
okay and so there's sort of a culture of
people posting things about you know
surprising things that cats do or dogs
do and there's a kind of a language that
develops around the recognition of you
know there's a certain I'm gonna botch
it but you know there's good boy kind of
thing for when a dog does something
really impressive and I'm watching I'm
noticing that you know people are
talking about these things on reddit or
wherever and they don't know whether
they are on the same side of the
political aisle all right they don't
know anything about each yeah but the
fact that you know yeah it might be that
I have a hard time seeing you right but
if you and I
looking at that dog the fact is our
human relationship with dogs is
universal enough right that we can
actually come together so yeah I had
that same exact similar experience with
DJing because when I first moved to New
York I discovered New York and
discovered when was this this is in 2015
okay I discovered Brooklyn and you know
some of my friends took me out to these
crazy parties in Brooklyn to see these
awesome DJs who are super talented and
I've always been fascinated with this
this thing that happens at concerts were
people are willing to stand as close as
possible to the other person that they
don't know in order to get as close as
possible to the stage and so like what
is it about that particular landscape
that that allows people to let
themselves be vulnerable essentially but
to also it's a different style or a
different kind of connection that occurs
in that type of landscape and the same
is true for the dance floor and when you
have a good DJ so what is it because
because you know two people dancing
together who have just met each other on
the dance floor could have two totally
different political viewpoints right or
two could see not even just politics but
could see the world fundamentally and I
told in totally different ways and yet
what is going on that dance floor is
it's powerful enough to have the people
there not care or that's not even they
understand that that is not the meaning
of life that's not the essence of life
in that moment and even if it's just for
a moment
they understand that whether or not they
share the same political opinions is not
really what is meaningful in that moment
right so that would never really be a
thing to come up or it would it
certainly wouldn't be the first thing to
come up it would be this this attempt at
connection period and so what is it
about the generation of the music
happening with the DJ that conjures up
and how can you take that bottle that
and then put it into a landscape like
Twitter for example or is it even
possible to do that alright that's quite
amazing
so I think you're being even a little
cautious and talking of what you're
proposing about two people on a dance
floor okay as if I if I modeled this
based on
experience of people if two people met
in the circumstance you're talking about
yeah
and they found themselves on a dance
floor together and they danced well
together
yeah which has a whole meaning to it
whatever that meaning is right I'm
convinced we haven't unpacked it enough
okay let's say two people experienced
they they groove well together sure
right and then they discover that they
do have some differences difference yeah
opinion that is supposed to be
unbreachable right it totally changes
the nature that they view that
difference it heavily not only does it
predispose them to find you know because
they have connected in this sort of
mysterious mystical way that dancing
involves right
they then a know that there is something
right that person is not the monster
connected to them you're already
connected in some deep way yeah so you
could find your way back there yeah and
you have an incentive to figure out well
surely that thing that we differ over
have be the sum total of it because and
it negates whatever it was implied by
the dance right and it also it has to be
because otherwise it would indict you
right it would mean that you know you
would it would mean that you had danced
with the enemy right I mean that some
that the enemy shared some aspects of
you had some aspect of you in them and
vice versa oh I love this so I think
this is the stuff that right it's very
very deep yeah yeah
well that's marvelous yeah so how do we
get it to Twitter well so I'm this is a
weird week for us to be talking about
this because my life on Twitter which is
four years been completely been a
terrible match for what people say about
the bitterness and rancor and inability
to discuss things over years Heather and
I have both had the experience of
finding most of Twitter pretty
respectful of us and pretty ready to
listen ready to you know admit error
when they say something intemperate and
then you know this week that's turned on
me okay as a result I think mostly or
entirely of my going too far in
challenging ah what I called New
Atheists not realizing that that was a
heavily charged
mmm-hmm in any case this is a rough week
for me on Twitter but but in general
yeah I do think we all see a different
Twitter and we don't necessarily know it
because there's only one name for it oh
right right yeah and so yeah when people
talk about you know how terrible twitter
is for discussion I know they're not
having my experience right all right all
right so how do we get it there in part
we've got an antagonist we don't know
because we don't know what role the AG
algorithms are playing you search
Twitter we see okay
but I think there's something about my
experience has been that figuring out
how to bridge gaps you're not supposed
to be able to bridge is actually kind of
addictive and I regarded as a positive
addiction okay all right it's like yeah
addicted to making music or okay yeah
and so in some sense I think the answer
to your question must be that if you can
just simply get people where they have
the experience of making a connection
with somebody they're not supposed to
like and that connection being rewarding
then it's almost self catalyzing I see
do you think that has happened in real
life though and not on online because
but like I would I it's actually I would
argue it would have to happen in real
life otherwise it doesn't work and I can
have psychologic has to translate to
real that's a translator life okay but
it could happen on Twitter first okay
yeah so maybe like seeing a video where
that happened and then it triggered some
emotion in them that was very pleasing
well I mean I think you know there are
these videos I've forgotten the
gentleman's name but this black guy who
decided to go and talk to Klan members
Oh Darryl Davis early yeah yeah I mean
we teach him in creeks Oh perfect sense
to it so I must say on the one hand I
totally relate to what he's up to it's
think you know that thing I was talking
about where yeah I feel the challenge
yeah I can imagine that he feels that
yeah feels that challenge you know he's
obviously extremely bold to do it right
in the way that he does but I think
there's a way in which
for almost all of us yeah you got to be
really cold yeah not to look at what
he's done and feel like a warm sense of
shared humanity over what he's able to
do and in fact even just seeing him on
screen with former Klan members yeah who
he's brought to their senses is you know
it's it's a feel-good story for the ages
definitely so it's got to be modeled
okay little experiences have to be
available to people um you know and it's
got to be small enough steps that they
can get there but the key message I
think for all of us who are good at
crossing gaps is that in the end it's a
it's a richer experience of life so yeah
I think that that is true I think that
that last bit is definitely it has to be
the objective and it has to be the goal
that we measure like this process that
we're talking about creating whether
it's successful or not but it turns out
that like I don't know if it's possible
to have deep enriching moments be
translated on social media because the
nature of deep enriching moments or deep
deep inverting feeling is such that I
don't think it could happen on a in the
landscape like so like it requires real
life real-world experience all that type
of process in order that's happened well
I hate to go all fractal on you oh I
lost the argument no you have it here's
the thing yeah we are engaged in a
conversation sure and you know there's
some people who aren't gonna like it but
yeah most people well most people who
are just to tell them that we still have
empathy for them and we care about them
yes welcome back anytime they come to
their senses
yes but the thing is we're doing this
sure and it weren't you know there's a
reason that we're doing this long-form
rather short form but this will go on
social
right yeah my guess is that some number
of people will even if they can't put
their finger on what it is that they've
experienced they will appear you and me
talking and they will understand I mean
sure you know my experience at Evergreen
was that a lot of people needed to hear
somebody say what they couldn't write
and having heard it
it's fractal a synonym for meta no this
way the very loose sense you could use
it that way but ok fractal means that
some process is scale independent the
point is you see you see the same
process that certainly different scales
okay so for example the example I've
heard people use that simplest is if you
were descending on the lunar lander onto
the surface of the Moon and you saw a
crater you couldn't tell how far away
from the moon you were because there are
craters at every size and so right right
you know the distribution of the craters
is okay fractal so all I'm saying is
that the the process that happens inside
of you know a particularly delightful
exchange of one-sentence also happens at
the level of an hour or two hours
inverse a ssin okay the level of a
that's fair college class actually yes
that makes sense
my entire startup it's promised upon
this working because it argues that you
can sort of you can gain those deep
enriching moments by consuming pop
culture which usually happens through a
medium and not necessarily in in person
meaning you go to the movie theater to
watch a movie and you experience this
you read a book and you experience this
you listen to a song and you experience
this so there is some medium that people
are consuming and they're still feeling
that larger experience so I guess that
makes sense yeah so I think we're caught
in a funny place okay pop culture okay
um and I realize you know you're using
pop culture to great effect and even if
most of pop culture were worthless it
wouldn't mean that there wasn't enough
of value to be mined there to spend a
lifetime doing what you're
so there's no indictment here from me of
what you're up to but I do have the
sense that pop culture works for what
you're doing because we are wired for
certain truths and therefore when those
truths are uttered by somebody appealing
in the public sphere
lots of people gravitate to it so it
generates wealth yes that causes it to
be broadcast nice so there's a way in
which the resonant message is you know
the record companies are a parasite on
the exchange of relevant messages
between people who feel them and those
who are listening right on the other
hand the market obviously distorts that
relationship to it'll tell you what you
want to hear rather than what you need
to know sure and that's very dangerous
so for the moment I don't know where we
are but you know it's it's so far it is
impossible to get a computer to generate
really compelling it can probably
generate music that mirrors something
that's already been produced but it's
hard for it to produce something
creative novel and compelling at least
at the level of lyrics so it would
generate what's on the top 100 today
right you could generate some slightly
novel sounds exactly like because of the
state at the top 100 today yeah rather
than somebody telling you something deep
right but you know so let's let's take a
favorite example for people of my
generation okay
the matrix okay yeah perfect for this
conversation perfect for this guy well
the matrix is in effect planos cave yes
right it's a very ancient yeah right you
know it's Plato's cave and it was wildly
successful because the production values
were super high and the story was
compelling and the modern twist wasn't
superficial so in the sense you know a
lot of people who had no relationship to
Plato's cave wouldn't know what Plato's
cave was or people who did know what it
was but didn't have a particularly deep
relationship with the stories it
suddenly had that story react sure our
experience by this very vivid you know
presentation of it and that's really
important I mean I
personally feel like Plato's cave is a
very deep story because this is a very
deep vulnerability for human beings the
fact that you know the the person who
escapes Plato's cave gets killed upon
re-entering and trying to know the truth
Wow does that one hit home yeah what are
the implications of that in your opinion
well the implications of that are a the
idea that you can simply speak truth to
power or the truth will out or any of
these things is it's a naive fiction
okay those who wish to unearth deep
truths should understand what business
they've gotten involved in okay
interesting but anyway I've sidetracked
us here this is all sidetracking it's
great that we can find out where that
way oh no that's interesting trying to
see if I could see we were saying I
could also see the opposite though being
the case I'm sure it is sometimes but
yeah anyway meaning well when I think
about what you said I think about you
know the challenge to dr. King quoting
William Cullen Bryant like the dark
what's what's the quote the about the
universe
no the arc of the moral universe annul
t'me is that these are competing forces
sure what what Star Wars II yep well
very Star Wars is very biblical yeah
yeah and but the I think the the point
about the devastating thing about Martin
Luther King Junior's invocation of the
arc of the moral universe yes is the
first part that is LARC of the moral
ours is long and he's telling you is you
might have to wait a very long time to
see it bend towards just yes that's it
that's a devastating
revelation yes well I don't know if it's
devastating
I'd say it's daunting I wouldn't
necessarily use it war devastating I
think is devastating to an individual
because the point is you live in an era
that's just brutal and that there's no
comfort as an individual to the idea
that eventually what was that things
will get better fixed right um on the
other hand at the lineage level that
that's important and it is reassuring to
know that even if you never escaped a
particular injustice that your kids or
your grandkids might see it reversed
right but they might not according to
your interpretation of the implication
of Plato's cave so well let's put it
this way I know Plato's cave is right
I've seen that one
I hope dr. King was right yes and that
in the end Plato's cave doesn't win okay
right sure in the end the revelation of
what's outside the cave right can't be
stopped because it is in fact true but
but to be fair play the Plato's cave
ends at a certain point meaning we don't
see what happens afterwards it could've
very well have been that this person
could have affected let's type that be
hypothetical for a moment some people
outside of that cave who saw his great
courage and valor and decided to follow
suit absolutely right so it's
interesting like to note where the book
ends and what the implication of that is
on society I would say that I do think
that um I do think that dr. King's
vision would ultimately win out though
just because the very fact that Plato
wrote that book would suggest a toying
with the notion of these concepts of
freedom and liberty and equality and
speaking truth to power like in writing
that he is writing a book about speaking
truth to power even if the person fails
in the end so very idea speaking truth
the power that becomes invented in that
moment and that in and of itself is
bending toward justice well I agree and
I not only hope that dr. King was right
yeah but at some level if he's not right
I don't know what there is I just don't
know what the point of right size is
right right
yeah he is right then the point is well
all right we all get dealt a hand and we
have to play it sure and some of them
are
better than others but but at least
we're headed in a direction of
improvement yes so actually if I might I
my grandfather was quite old in his in
his 80s okay we started keeping accounts
current okay that he was very clear on
the fact that he wasn't gonna live
forever and that meant that we should
probably say what needed to be said
mm-hmm before I was too late sure which
was very uncomfortable at first and then
it became very normal and I recommend it
to everyone okay
there's somebody you care about yeah
because they won't be around forever but
at some point I asked him he had in my
whole experience of him he had railed
against the injustice of the system and
the brokenness all of the things that we
did wrong that were relatively
transparent mm-hmm and I asked him if
there was a period in time that he would
like to go back to in his life rather
than live in the present given how much
he saw was wrong with it and he
surprised me he said absolutely not yeah
and I said I'm shocked you completely
know much about the way things are yeah
and he says you have no idea about the
profound ignorance of the past mm-hmm
right and I was just you know I stopped
in my tracks as I hadn't really
understood he was impatient for things
to get better right that's what the
complaining was but he had no illusions
about where we had come from right and
that enlightenment was frustratingly
slow and it moves and fits and starts
it can even go backwards but in general
we are much clearer headed than we were
mm-hmm reminds me of dr. King's last
speech where he says sort of in a very
like gospel way he basically paints this
picture of his creator asking him if he
could choose to be in any era where
would it be and then he goes sort of
like this these biblical narratives of
like the children in Israel and he would
not stop there and I think he actually
mentions Plato and Socrates and he said
I would not stop there and he goes
through Athens and he goes to Greece and
he goes to I think certain time
in America's early history and then he
finally says that he would pick the here
and now to be in and it's like actually
a very beautiful speech and if your
viewers haven't seen it I highly
recommend they do but yeah it's like and
if you know if you don't have any
ignorance of the past then you're more
likely to be able to recognize that you
actually have made progress like
relatively speaking right and so so yeah
you'll be impatient but you'll probably
be more imbued with that same spirit of
it's long but it's obviously bending
because look where we were before yeah I
I think that's absolutely right and I
almost wonder in your retelling that if
my grandfather was not in some way
referencing consciously or not yeah
you're right it's yeah yeah it's the
same point that's cool yeah so I I must
say I personally fear that although I
think dr. King was right and it gives me
hope I fear that there's a pattern in
human behavior I've written about it
actually scientifically many years ago
but I fear that there's a basically a
flip-flop okay between how human beings
behave in times of growth times of
Plenty and how human beings behave in
times of contraction of economic
contraction or its equivalent and that
in fact the arc of history or the arc of
the moral universe may be long and bend
towards justice but that it actually
flips back and forth rather violently
and this actually raises another
interest of yours which will surprise my
viewers who don't know you and I'm not
surprised those who have heard you speak
elsewhere but you have a very deep
relationship with Judaism yes and
anti-semitism yes and in writing it
folks
yes absolutely oh right it was I unclear
about that oh man that's terrible
so why don't you just tell us where that
relationship comes from and what it
means to you and then we can go for
there and okay draw the connection I was
headed for sure so I was born and raised
in a very atypical Christian family grew
up in a Christian family
observe things like Shabbat and
kosher-style and all the holy days from
our show notes yom kippur very similar
to seven-day business but that naturally
allowed the development or created the
development of an affinity for Judaism
because that was the closest community
that did the same thing as me basically
and so you know in high school I joined
the Hebrew culture club I read books by
Leon URIs which were all about three
establishment of the State of Israel
initially majored in film in college but
then switched to International Studies
because anti-semitism was resurfacing in
Europe at the time this isn't like 2012
and then after that I started a student
pro-israel Club at the University of New
Orleans and did it so advocacy for three
and a half years and then after that
works for two years in the Israel space
Israel nonprofit space interesting so so
many things far be it for me to define
you in any way but I just try to
understand okay you're not Jewish now
but you have a deep cultural affinity
for is what is it is it the Jewish
religion is it its people or what kind
of all of it
you know I don't know if a catch-all
term but I guess it's culture I guess
culture is a word that would carry all
of that what could hold all of those
terms
so I'd say culture okay very broadly
speaking very broadly speaking yeah okay
well I find this fascinating I'm
obviously Jewish um I don't have a
particularly deep relationship with the
religion I have I what I think is a very
deep relationship with the culture of
the Diaspora okay but anyway you know
I'm not I'm not observant sure and so
anyway I have I have a kind of distance
from Judaism that happened I didn't
choose it it comes as sort of is where I
ended up but it's very interesting to
hear somebody from the outside of the
population who finds an affinity
for the style of thinking or something
about it and it you know raises all
kinds of questions for me about well the
connection I was going to draw that sent
us down this road was Jews are a kind of
an odd phenomenon okay you tend to exist
at low density okay you know in a
diaspora sure if you asked me as an
evolutionary biologist how likely is
that to work as a long-term strategy for
persisting on earth I would say the
chances are almost zero okay all right
it's too dangerous
sure right the fact is having a majority
population that can always turn on you
sure is it's a tremendous hazard that
looms always and the boom-and-bust cycle
issue that I was talking about basically
I think like in plenty and in scarcity
right the society you know plenty it may
be the Jews are tolerated but as things
turned towards austerity anti-semitism
rises again and the amazing thing is
that Jews have persisted for the long
period of time that they have and I
think these that fact and the high level
of success the Jews have experienced and
things like advancing science at cetera
sure
I suspect they are coupled okay that in
effect Jews I hate the idea of it shows
and people okay I think it's time that
humans got over that idea sure but just
for your stuff so your viewers no no no
that won't happen the arc of the moral
I don't like the idea of chosen people
because I find it there's something
wrong with the idea that if there was a
creator created some people he didn't
choose Christo I don't Barbra I
understand your objection to it and a
little from literal sense yeah but if
you were looking at impress on a deeper
psychological level it could be the case
that it's important to have a chosen
people because then other people will
think that it is possible that they too
could be chosen well first of all I
should just say I'm not a I'm not a
believer in the supernatural sure so in
a sense
even thinking about it as a literal
matter I don't even know what to do with
it okay but my sense is that we are
better off considering this is probably
also uncomfortable because declaring any
thing about any racial group special
sure especially if it's one you belong
to sure have some problems it smacks of
arrogance or hubris or something but
anyway my point would be maybe not the
chosen people but maybe the anti fragile
people and that means that basically the
amount of hazard per era mm-hmm that
Jews have faced has created a kind of
ability to survive in all kinds of
extreme circumstances what has not
killed us has made us stronger in a way
now personally yes I suspect that what
is special is transmitted culturally
sure and therefore to the extent it is
valuable it can be democratized sure I
don't know if that's right but okay I
don't know okay as far as I know it's
wait what was the lesson use that to the
extent that it is culture it can be
democratized yeah right well I have it
this way if it was genetic right right
if the fact of many trials and
tribulations had created special genes
sure there'd be nothing you could do
about it other than I see breed them out
as I mean breed them out into the other
population but that doesn't necessarily
mean that culture can be democratized
well this ultra can be Democritus
because and in fact you're the proof no
but I'm an anomaly well and you were
this is a totally uncontrolled
experiment in a sense that you know
there's nothing there's nothing about
this that is controlled I'm sure
everybody is idiosyncratic sure
including you but the point is you
Judaism is not a recruiting religion
right it does not seek converts right
in fact it sort of looks askance at
people who wish to join sure but it
allows it yes um
and you have taken an interest in the
culture yes and have absorbed the
meaning of that culture yes very deeply
sir right so that's that's the meaning
of democratizing of culture I guess I
don't know if it's the process by which
that happened it's really scalable well
I'm not really because I have pathetical
so as a college professor when I was a
college professor
I took the stuff that I had learned at
the dinner table about how to argue a
point how to hold other people's feet to
the fire how to back off when you
discovered that you something about your
thinking is incorrect how to gracefully
you know grant that fact and I taught
students to do it irrespective of their
background sure some part of me felt
like I was taking things that were very
common at a Jewish dinner table okay and
introducing them into the classroom and
later point I guess would be the unusual
level of success that Jews have
experienced in certain quadrants to the
extent that it is culturally transmitted
which may be all of it okay um I I find
it hard to imagine any of it is not
readily learning that's interesting I
don't know I wonder what that would look
like or that process would look like
well on a mass scale I've said this
elsewhere at least once I don't remember
where exactly but the I think the other
proof of this is the Enlightenment okay
which was not a Jewish project sure but
Jews myself included have taken those
tools and wielded them
effectively and at some level I feel
like the Enlightenment was an
achievement it was a human achievement
mm-hmm it belongs to everybody
sure right and this is one of the things
that breaks my heart about the
intersection of movement and the present
is the rejection of the Enlightenment
which state will flatter
flatly tell you they want to see if your
enlightenment is somehow biased and
white and ready to be tossed out right
well my feeling is no actually what it
needs to be done what needs to be done
with it is it needs to be taught so
everybody has access to those tools you
know you're not you're not gonna beat
the scientific method which is it right
directly yeah the Enlightenment is a
product of the Enlightenment sure so in
any case the democratizing of those
tools that are acquired through some
sort of history seems to me the right
answer okay I think that perhaps the
intersectional left's objection to the
Enlightenment is proof that the very
least such as the marketization process
could be hindered later on because well
I you know because if they're rejecting
the Enlightenment which was the mock
sighs to certain extent
then you know I don't know maybe it's
just a back and forth a cyclical tension
that always keeps happening
for some reason well if we were to steal
men their point oh yes please do
I do think that there's a way in which
the attempt or the attempts to
democratize the benefits of for example
the Enlightenment have stalled okay and
so I think you know look I think a lot
of the people who are leading the
intersectional movement are actually
cynical actors serving themselves but I
don't think the average person in the
movement is cynical okay the average
person in the movement has been misled
okay but the the idea that something has
not worked about democratization of
these concepts and tools I'm all ears
the extent to which these tools are
themselves sure
problematic I find impossible to imagine
given how well they work and given that
their central value I mean the the
central value of the scientific method
is that it corrects for bias right sure
I think that's I think that's all too
well are you planning on conducting an
experiment to see if Judaism can be
democratized I mean I don't know how to
say this without seeming like a weirdo
but I sort of think that we're engaged
in that right here and that's what we're
figuring out right I don't think it's
just me at this moment
oh yeah it's you and me okay um I was in
it's like it's like the matrix when you
wake up and you realize what's going on
right well what I mean you know but I
don't know if it's a conscious thing
it's like oh might not be and I might be
a might be a foolish thing to even say
out loud yeah I mean I wouldn't go that
far but but yeah I don't I don't know
the implications I don't know if I need
to know the implications of what that
would mean but it's a cool thing to
think about I guess well is the maybe
let me rephrase those okay point this
way and try it out on you okay
the Greeks yeah discovered a very power
powerful tool kit for thought okay for
mathematical proof mm-hmm etc mm-hmm it
was a discovery of the Greeks but it
doesn't belong to the Greek sir all
right everybody gets to use trig sure
the Galileo huh
obviously innovated a perspective that
allowed us to understand things about
our physical universe and our place in
it yet
are not
his property not the property of choice
people but they are human achievements
okay
when Americans landed on the moon in
1969 Americans may have viewed it as an
American achievement and it was sure but
there's also a way in which people all
over the world viewed it as a human
achievement and it was sure right I feel
like I know where this is going right
well I'm yeah it is going and it is it
is it is apparently there but the basic
point is look stuff is gonna get
discovered by some population first it's
just inevitable that it will and some
stuff is going to get discovered many
places that aren't in contact which I
mean farming was discovered five
different places released right across
the planet does that mean that people
who don't come from a population that
discovered had a farm are not entitled
to do it of course not right so anyway
the question is is not the most noble
viewpoint on how we are to move forward
as a species that wherever valuable
stuff is discovered the insights
belonged to all of us you don't discover
on behalf of your population you
discover on behalf of enlightenment so I
think it's a great question by the way
well done I think really a good question
so I think that it's the answers both
and this is a paradox so but I think the
answer can be that both in one sense
when you discover something it's on
behalf of humanity but also and yes they
are the how did you put it they are the
they belong to everyone and like anyone
can practice trigonometry right so I
think that's true but I think it's also
true that human beings need and are
wired for story and so from that
perspective the idea of having a story
which sort of maps out a direction that
gives meaning to your life is also
itself necessary for human development
so it's necessary for human development
to be able to say we can
all use trigonometry but it's also
necessary for human development tell the
particular story whether we're talking
about in the form of Judaism or I'm just
saying story in general is necessary for
the for human psyche I think because
that's what we're wired for so we're
measuring two different values
essentially in this conversation one
value is the value of like the value of
the collective and this is actually a
very Jewish thing to say but one value
is the value of the collective and one
value is the value of the individual and
so the question is how do you balance
those two things because both of them
are necessary in terms of how we shape
the stories that we tell our lives
it is incredibly moving to think about
you know the landing on the moon being
an achievement for all of humanity and
sort of like a what a feeling of oneness
with all of what all human beings on the
other hand we do know that it is very
hard to conceptualize a statistic of
multiple people dying as opposed to one
individual dying right and so we are
wired as such that we need we need the
cosmic but we also need the particular
we need the universal but we also need a
particular and the challenge is how to
how to balance both of those things in a
healthy way beautiful now here's the
question that I suspect haunts this
analysis okay which is yep you got the
individual yeah you've got the
collective but which collectives okay
and so what I see after decades of study
of history evolution human nature
mmm-hmm what I see is a tragic story in
which we are built to cooperate mm-hmm
to compete and cooperate to compete
that's what we do we operate in order to
complete cooperate in order to compete
and in and of itself that is not
inherently bad it results in all sorts
of marvelous things but it is the the
seed of our undoing is in that formula
because we have gotten more and more
power
in that process and the ability to play
that competition to a fatal end is
looming sure nearby because of
Technology because of technology because
of the size of the population and
because of the interconnectedness okay
which we live okay
and the question is there's been a
process in which the collective has been
broadened historically so if I think for
example of the story of the Good
Samaritan yeah
the Golden Rule which evolves in
multiple traditions yes there's a ll
version and the Jesus version but these
stories create a context for broadening
the circle with whom you collaborate
sure why in order to compete with
something outside of it but we are now
linked together in a way that we have to
collaborate all of us the collective
there is a collective which is all of us
okay right
it hasn't successfully collaborated sure
yet sure if it doesn't we've got a big
problem and my guess would be it's a
fatal problem in the near term but we
are not wired for it because cooperate
to compete works up until there's no one
to compete with ah right and so in some
sense we have to level ourselves up and
hence the need for the chosen people no
hence the need for us to take all of the
the important discoveries that different
populations have made and pull them and
there's one way in which you could take
this as some sort of you know utopian
okay all is one yeah viewpoint oh and
what I'm saying is that the difficulty
is that the story in which we all
realize you know what astronaut
typically realize yeah they look back at
the earth and they sir have what's
called the overview effect right that
that experience somehow has to be
translated to everybody
yeah the discoveries that each
population have made that are valuable
has to be democratized okay and that we
are not wired for that transition even
if we require it is a daunting challenge
okay I see you're saying yes I was gonna
say I don't know if that's possible to
translate all the sort of discoveries of
every community to the entire circle
meaning the meaning meaning to say that
you all we all inherit this or this is
our inheritance all of us collectively I
don't know I don't know if that's
possible
well okay at the risk of pushing this
somewhere three uncomfortable oh okay
yes sorry um at the risk of doing that
can we talk about the predicament of the
population of people who arrived in the
new world for the purpose of functioning
as slaves
I mean sure this is a population that
you drive from on both sides you sure
that population a was many populations
mm-hmm in Africa yeah but that
population that assembled here yes as a
purpose of doing the labor yes of the
population with power right it had its
culture systematically destroyed sure
right now yeah hundred percent yeah but
to a great extent yeah for the purpose
of making enslavement function right
that population therefore does not have
access mmm-hmm to the ancestral sure the
garrisons right its language destroyed
or its languages destroyed at its
coherent set of cultural traditions
largely disrupted
so the point is that population actually
has to take on another sum it doesn't
have to be one populations package of
discoveries but it has to take on
something to replace that which was
stolen from oh that's interesting
am I wrong about that I wouldn't
necessarily think about it in this in in
these terms because if certain elements
of culture are universal and thus can be
found in every culture then technically
one could guess that the things that
that the things that we're taking from
other cultures were also part of our
culture at some point even before it was
destroyed um well let me let me come at
that biologically and just look at my
best guess okay
people are very similar yes their
capacity to discover yes see you know if
you take a Guns Germs and Steel view of
history which I very definitely do what
you basically see is that human beings
inherited very uneven pieces of turf
okay and that those very uneven pieces
of turf caused some populations to move
faster sure and some populations to move
slower based on for example how many
domesticable animals are available to
them sure there was a concentration of
domesticable animals above you know the
size of a rabbit um you know in Asia
right and there was a deficit of them in
New World example so that is to say the
ones that exist in the New World Network
transported from Asia and via Europe
right my merrily but but people are
basically people will discover what
there is to discover the rates at which
they discover these things are heavily
dependent on idiosyncrasies of the
environment that they inherit just by
virtue of where they are on earth and so
I don't think there is any reason to
imagine that a many of these things were
discovered in various places in the
earth or across the earth and that in
places where they hadn't been discovered
yet they would
right you know we can see in mesoamerica
for example a highly sophisticated
culture that was a few hundred years
behind Europeans in terms of metallurgy
okay all right maybe it's a thousand
years behind but it doesn't yeah vast
distance in historical context and the
point is well that created a military
disadvantage that was absolutely
unbeatable when Europeans showed up but
but my point is I agree that populations
that have had their culture disrupted
mm-hmm either had those discoveries in
their history or would have come across
them soon enough sure but from the point
of view of where we all land now sure I
think the point is well we've got
libraries sure they're full of these
discoveries yeah why don't we just make
sure that a package that contains all of
the most useful stuff is given to every
little yeah yes made available I don't I
think that's fine I think that's a
that's a it's a different analogy but I
I think it's a good solution to well
we've sort of meandered from this
particular verse is the universal two
who inherit what's or proof that there
has to be this approach that says that
everyone would have access to the the
gifts that all communities are all
ancient people have created or
discovered because if you run into a
situation like people's history being
wiped out they will need to take from
other people's histories or other
people's accomplishments and also be
able to call it their own but I think
they're able to call it their own
because they're human beings not because
of where they come from or because of
even the even the origin so I think that
the fact of the human being that we are
human beings transcends all of that and
so that is why for example African
Americans have a right to that heritage
not because not because it's useful but
because it is and this is I can't prove
this but because it is because it's a
metaphysical statement
it is objectively the case that what
transcends all of that is the dignity of
the human person yeah I think in fact
well I think these are two facets of the
same coin and okay I agree that if we
taught but yeah if we if we acknowledge
the dignity of the human person and like
what that entails we also have to
recognize that in order to thrive I
think human beings need stories and not
stories just of the collective but also
stories of the particular and so you
know so to ask the question which is a
challenging question it's very good
question why can't the accomplishments
for example of the Jewish people be the
collective accomplishments of all of
humanity right I supposed to see this is
very specific thing but a particular
thing in a sense because scale Lil's
accomplishments are not seen as the
Italian people is a conference right
right so there's this difference there
but I don't necessarily think that
there's anything wrong with the
difference oh I don't think there's
anything wrong with the difference and
I'm not looking to sanitize or
neutralize the stories at all it's not
even really the accomplishments you know
well I guess accomplishments is maybe
too vague it's the tools hmm it's the
tools that I see as an absolutely vital
that we democratize everybody needs
access to those tools and to the extent
that our cooperate to compete modality
has brought us to this place
it has also caused us to wield tools and
to deny them to others sure that that's
that's the key strategy yes I'm gonna
discover a tool I'm going to wield it to
benefit me and whatever I identify as
self sure right and I'm going to deny it
to those with whom I am competing so
interesting in light it's interesting
notion in light of the fact that some
intersectional lists reject the
Enlightenment all right yes cuz it's a
reverse thing because you would think
that many people in who hold this
political ideology believe that they do
so in the name of minority groups
well you're saying is there if you've
rejects these tools which are the
inheritance of all of humanity then
you're doing something that's actually
fundamentally undemocratic you're like
reversing that democratic process yes
and it's so self-defeating yes because
you're you're only hurting yourself
essentially because you're denying
yourself access to the tool which is
actually your inheritance as a human
being it's your inheritance and yeah
this is exactly this is exactly my
frustration is that I have the sense
there is really something to the idea
that some people have been shut out of
access to those tools and instead of
demanding access to those tools right
they are declaring the tools right
illegitimate and biased which is not the
case right that's interesting yeah
that's that's very strange
yeah it is very strange it's very
disheartening yeah and yeah it's sort of
it's jarring given what Heather and I
were doing trying to pass those tools on
the people in taking great pleasure and
watching them acquire that and wield
them with ever more skill but sure
though there has to be a parable that
can teach us about this like there has
to be a peril parable were like I don't
know the child rejected the tools that
the parents tried to give them or
something along those lines yeah I'm
sort of like sift through and try to
predict what's gonna what's gonna be the
outcome of this new pattern of behavior
that we're seeing I agree there should
be there should be a well-known story
but I can't think yeah yeah um why am i
blanking on the author of the idea that
the masters house cannot be disassembled
with the Masters tools oh I don't know
that one you don't know that one I find
this a very I see it periodically the
masters house cannot be disassembled
with the Masters tools because the
master built it and so I have to say
this was an idea that people wield
mm-hmm and I can't make sense of it I
can it sort of sounds right until you
think about the implications and my
feeling is
well I just don't know what it means
well it means that you know it's
obviously a reference to to slavery okay
the master sure has tools and if you
want a dismantled slavery you can't do
it with the tools that belong to the
master feeling third it's absurd that's
absurd it's not only a fundamental it's
fallen would have ripped that apart it's
the opposite of the beds absurd
right that is like the literal Wow I
hadn't heard that nobody's got better
tools in the master right go with the
master shed the master has the finest
tools in town if you were gonna use
tools to dismantle the Masters house
those would be the ones I can't believe
I'm blanking on it I used to know what
like the back of my hand but not that I
know the back of my head I've never
understood that expression but yeah I
was thinking I'm sure there are more
implications for this statement because
that's just I mean first of all the of
the the audacity to assume that see this
is the point this is the problem that I
have this is the thing that frustrates
me what is what is at the essence or
what connects the master and the slave
in this paradigm that we are we are
talking about because in the book as a
man liveth the author says be neither a
master nor a slave and in the
conversation with Nikki Giovanni and
James Baldwin in the 70s Nikki Giovanni
says there are only two people that are
hated the worst in this world and that
is the master and slave so almost like
trying to promote this rejection of that
paradigm as a starting point but anyway
even if we were to take that paradigm as
a starting point it's like what is what
is at the base of these two categories
is a human being and so this idea it's
like it's so antithetical to its so
fundamentally untrue because because on
a on a sort of I don't know how to put
this on a deeper level both of you are
human being so both of you can exhibit
certain qualities and certain behaviors
that are either destructive or
productive or moral or immoral right so
this idea that like
that one cannot even this goes back to
the beginning of our conversation that
one can't find the commonality or the
common humanists between these two
categories which would make a person
realize that that statement is silly
right is very dehumanizing actually
because it says that the essence of what
you are are these categories not the
human being underneath because if it's a
human being underneath then the slave
could take those same tools and make
something else right the point is not
the tools it's the being that's using
the tools and so this saying is regulus
because it takes the autonomy away from
the human being which is ironic because
the categories are master and slave but
this person does not come with the cat
up with the category of a free person or
a person who is free yeah all right the
person who's free does not fall into
either those categories a hundred
percent a hundred percent agree with
this and the question it's so
heartbreaking
because I have the sense that you know
let's take your example from the
beginning of the conversation to people
who find themselves moving together well
on a dance floor sure they come to have
some deep connection that isn't founded
on the content of their conscious
beliefs right okay and then their
conscious beliefs emerge in the
conversation afterwards sure right that
experience reveals something about the
very point you're making about the human
being
versus the status right right I have the
sense that this just isn't that hard and
we're still not gonna succeed at it what
do you mean it's not that hard that you
know when when I was facing the
protestors who became rioters at
Evergreen
mmm-hmm I kept having the sense that
these people had you know let's put the
bad actors aside there were some bad
actors out of them but then there were a
lot of people who were saying stuff like
the Masters okay yes can't be
disassembled with
masters tools and I had the sense you
know what these guys need they need a
really good college course that takes
months that runs you through these well
but the tragedies of a college coming
apart over the fact that what the people
who were tearing it apart needed was
calling right looks like oh we've got a
college here can't yeah can we not well
I say use these buildings and the things
that you're saying let's take the things
that you're saying and let's start there
yeah let's just start there we'll take
them as a premise and yeah see how well
that premise stands up this is not that
hard right right but it was impossible
okay and so I guess maybe that's what
I'm getting at is that I'm a little bit
heartbroken okay something that where
the parameters slightly changed it's not
that hard
it comes impossible so what's parameters
needs would need to change in order for
it to well you know you mentioned
something about conservatives and
self-government I think was the term
that you used there is a way in which
yes there is a problem with the
structures of authority people are sick
and tired of being told that their
system functions and if they just keep
their head down and do their work they
will end up in a decent place because
they can see that that's not inherently
true sure right so the frustration makes
sense but the allergic reaction to all
structures right as if it is the fact of
the structures that is oppressing that's
wrong and so I guess my point is I'm
very upset at the state of the
university system I think the university
system has abdicated responsibility for
teaching and it's taken up some other
kinds of jobs in order to pay the rent
but its failure to teach has resulted in
a lot of people who haven't learned and
having not learned they aren't in a
position to evaluate the quality of what
they're asserting the system should look
like
so they're saying patently absurd things
about you know what the rules of society
ought to be and you know we can't afford
to try out their experiment right right
it will be an absolute disaster so this
has to be taught in the abstract rather
than trying it okay so anyway I guess my
point is look I don't think I think a
lot of college professors don't do a lot
of teaching and Isis isn't just college
for yeah it's teachers that's crazy
it's crazy good to think about to
imagine yeah but what if what if it all
depends on getting people calm down to
step back and be systematic yeah okay
wait what are you claiming yeah and then
let's play it through well in order to
get my feeling is that the reason why
it's hard is because in order to get a
student to be able to do that that
student has to identify with that
process and so and this is where
identity in a more serious context can
be discussed so like house what is this
person's sense of self in the world how
does this person conceive of him or
herself this is a person know themselves
really and having known oneself is now
now being able to navigate the outside
world and specifically in reference to
the college campus for the purposes of
this conversation so it may be a person
is has to be raised in such a way or
nurtured in such a way that they would
want to or that they would be more
likely to respond to that okay so I
don't know this is perfect actually I
was thinking about this this morning
okay and preparing to talk to you about
it okay it's a question I have about
whether or not by theory of Enchantment
you mean something that is analogous to
an idea that motivated my teaching
something I use to describe my own
teaching to myself okay you have to give
me a little leeway okay the word
seduction
it has a bad connotation it's not
inherently sure bad but it has a sexual
connotation that doesn't belong in this
conversation sure but I I felt when I
was involved in teaching that good
teaching involved a kind of intellectual
seduction okay and what I mean by that
is the way to get somebody to learn is
not to take true things or things you
think are true and put them on the board
and make them read them and stuff like
that it doesn't work sure what does work
is showing them here is something that
you could have right and here is why you
want it
right and here is the path to get it
sure and it's not necessarily going to
be simple but the point is you're doing
it for you right you're doing it so that
at the end of this process you have a
tool to wield that will serve you for
the rest of your life yes right and if
done well right if done in a way you
know you do have to cultivate the trust
of the people that you are teaching
right right they really because if you
just walk in there and you say that
right they won't believe you right right
they're too jaded right if you allow
them to see your humanity which goes to
what you were saying before allow them
to see your humanity you show them that
you are dealing with them
straightforwardly
yeah and then you place the thing on
offer in my case it was evolutionary
toolkit that allows you to understand
what is otherwise a very confusing
predicament that you've landed in as a
human being okay that you will be more
in control mm-hmm of your life right
yeah you want to understand your love
life and not be so confused by it yeah
just so happens that love evolved in the
context of evolution and that that's why
it's so confusing and there's a map yeah
do you want it you know that yeah right
so anyway theory of Enchantment I guess
I'm wondering whether or not your use of
enchantment and my use of seduction or
are these synonyms are close or do you
mean something else I think that they
are close I don't think they're synonyms
I think that they are certainly related
to each other
enchantment so I picked the word in
chairman because at the time I was doing
this research paper that ended up being
the catalyst for the startup and I was
reading a book by Guy Kawasaki former
marketing director of Apple who wrote a
book called enchantment and enchantment
he defines it as like the process by
which you delight someone with a idea or
whether it's a person or a thing
whatever your delighting them to feel
fundamentally delighted and I think that
the similar to sort of like here's this
map do you want it that's sort of like
delighting them in a way but I think the
difference between the two is that well
I guess one of the differences that
comes to mind is that in your scenario
the delight comes in the fact that the
person is going out on an adventure to
try to go obtain a thing right that's
where the delight comes from whereas in
my curriculum the delight comes from
simply recognizing yourself and certain
truths about the world in things that
you did not know contained or could
resonate with you on that level so this
this is great this is better than I okay
it sounds to me like the distinction is
one between delight and entice yeah so
what I'm talking about is enticed yeah I
talk about delight
yeah yeah and I like both of these
they're neighboring tool yeah and yeah
yeah and it goes to something that I
also came to believe I don't know when
it actually dawned on me consciously but
by the end of my teaching career I had
come to believe that most of the
obstacle to students acquiring a deep
understanding of things was not about
content
okay it's about motivation okay their
motivation well the teachers motivation
sort of sets the course the teachers
motivation is screwed up sure it's very
hard even if the students are well
motivated for it to go anywhere positive
but in general students are badly wired
to acquire useful stuff okay the one
thing II
the really good students yeah tend to be
wired to please the authority figure at
the front of the room and so they end up
inadvertently effectively gaming the
system because they get good at getting
a pat on the head from the teacher and I
know from experience somebody who gets
really good at that game right they're
getting straight A's
but what they've learned is how to
please that person and one of two things
happens to them when they graduate
either that person at the front of the
room gets replaced by a boss right and
now they've become a cog because what
they've got right that is pleasing
somebody who has authority of RAM or
they can't figure out what to do right
because the person at the front of the
room was the source of their motivation
right okay right and so yeah in some
sense you have to if I've run into a
student who's very capable hmm but it's
not internally motivated mm-hmm that
becomes my focus okay my point is look
you got a hazard built into you you've
got everything you need to succeed sir
but you've got a hazard built into you
which is that until you take over your
own ability to direct your ship you're
either gonna belong to somebody else or
you're gonna be adrift sure so anyway
motivation is the key so anyway you
could do this with delight and you can
do this with entice they both work play
on the motivate but the Buffy oh I see
does it is it affected by the fact that
it's the authoritarian saying here's the
road map you might want to try to follow
it that's a really interesting meaning
presumably anyone should be able to
replace the role of the authoritarian
and say it and if it's powerful if it's
enticing enough then the person will do
it regardless of who's also a Rotarian
staying it saying to do it is I really
like that yeah I think it so we've been
playing with a model where you've got
bad actors who have taken advantage of a
set of stories and rules that is
essentially structured to be gamed but
what you're saying it goes a step beyond
that I think and that in effect we have
predisposed people
to follow bad leaders by telling them
the key thing to do is to make somebody
with power happy sure that fits for me
sure I do think that that is a part of
what's going on but but there are
competing stories though that we've
because we also tell other stories
culturally yes but the I think the thing
that I find most frightening about the
intersectional story is that it offers
people are you know especially young
people tend to be looking for the
equivalent of a get-rich-quick scheme
okay some rapid way that they can get to
the place where they don't have to worry
about money and sure any of the other
difficult things to acquire in life and
so somebody who's selling a story in
which hey guess what you can find out
where you are in a magical pecking order
right here's the intersectional map
right you're on it somewhere right find
yourself right right now what we're
gonna do the intersectional map defines
a future in which we're gonna turn the
tables right right and so the people who
were way ahead they're gonna be way
behind because they don't have any
intersectional points at all right right
and so the fact is this is not likely to
be very compelling to people with
marginal sure intersectional credentials
but there are a whole lot of people who
have multiple axes on which they will
see themselves as oppressed and the
point is will huh if I sign up for this
vision sure maybe it's next week that
I'm in a better position so there has
just an alternative story that can
compete with that framework and I'll
turn a framework rather than story but
yeah cuz intersectionality is
fundamentally a story as you just said
so there has to be another story that
can go toe to toe with that story but I
think I think you were there earlier in
this conversation okay
and I think the point is oh what's the
master of the slave that would argue
that story no that's a good one and it's
relevant yeah but with the individual
and collective oh oh because the point
is that's our that intersectional story
yeah is
entirely collective sprite right right
and that this is you know lots of people
who have looked at this movement and
been frightened by it have recognized
that it involves a almost total
deindividuation right right even the
language which I understand its origin
of it okay black and brown bodies sure
that's yeah not a like it's very new
it's very new relatively recent and I
was hearing that in the 90s personally
yeah I wasn't yeah I mean I think it
comes from Tommy he's codes right um
that would make sense make sense okay
and I understand it I mean in fact in
fact I even think his point yeah I
understand it is right yeah right his
point if I understand his point
correctly his point is in order to
oppress ultimately it comes down to
control over somebody's body sure right
sure that's how you impress somebody
well hmm Baldwin might be a little bit
meta and a couple of quotes from I mean
this is I can't leave I'm doing this but
a couple of quotes from the Great
Debaters Wow okay so the Great Debaters
is based on with your story Denzel
Washington plays this coach who coaches
debaters it's during racial segregation
it's a South the team in stop competing
in Harvard and winning the entire like
you that's what the movies about but
this is incredible scene where this is
one guy who's really smart really
talented but also has problems with
authoritarian figures and just lashing
out because everything that was done to
him and so Denzel Washington says to him
in this monologue he explains to him how
during slavery there was the development
of Willie Lynch ISM which lets you what
we now know as lynchings where the
purpose was to brutally brutally destroy
the black and brown body right
physically destroy right so so it's a
thomas equals this point that was the
goal and he says that the goal was to
keep them in line right so that they
would work without questioning without
protesting and so in that sense gave the
body back and but they took the mind
right so Denzel Washington says that was
the goal keep the body take the mind and
he says I am and every professor on this
campus are here to help you take back
keep or get back and keep your righteous
mind because obviously you have lost it
now I tell that story because not
because what Coates is saying is it
right I understand the essence of what
he's saying but there has been this
deeper thread I think within a lot of
the ideas that have pulsated through the
civil rights movement and the Harlem
Renaissance movement which is that
oppression is fundamentally about the
spirit about the mind and it's not yes
it's about the body but it's not simply
about the body and so coaches mistake is
in reducing the human being to the body
when in fact there was this belief in a
transcendent that the ultimate value lay
in the mind and in human consciousness I
know but I think it's relevant I know is
it perfect challenges that framework it
doesn't it's not to say that the
framework isn't correct but it isn't the
deepest truth yes the framework has a
piece of the truth right isn't the truth
right synonymous with it yes okay so
this is great so the body ends up being
oppressed yes it's not the entire point
the intersectional movement D
individuate it's allowed the minds have
you taken they did they give away the
Enlightenment and they gave away the
mind right which is which is to give
away the mind and the stories that they
tell are these mind-numbing stories
where achievements of an individual
don't even exist they're a myth of white
supremacy or something right right okay
so your question then is they've got a
story which is there's a map you can
find yourself on it and it's gonna
involve a reversal of oppression sure
and so how are you gonna be in a world
where we've reversed depression how are
you gonna be your probably gonna be
better off than you are so this is a
good story follow us sure right your
question is what's the old
native story right the alternative story
I believe is actually and I have to say
this is a story I have heard from I've
heard it from black conservatives okay
very regularly okay all right and it it
has caught my attention because okay as
I got in trouble for saying a little bit
on Joe Rogan's program mm-hmm I didn't
initially understand why there were
black conservatives okay it seemed to me
hard to imagine and as I've encountered
more and more of them I've come to
understand what the phenomenon isn't
it's okay
deep meaning which I respect greatly but
the the point is the empowerment of the
individual hmm right these are the
alternative story
sure you can entice right right you can
enchant right these are both mechanist
but the point is do you want a tool that
will make you more powerful mm-hmm well
let me tell you about the Enlightenment
right the Enlightenment is that it's not
the only tool but it's a major tool in
that toolkit of becoming more powerful
and having more control every life now
here is the thing that I think when I
talk to black conservatives and I hear
them talking about personal
responsibility right I think I know why
this has become such a focus and it is
because the ability to change the fate
of the collective it's not great right
right it's very hard to change the fate
of a population on the other hand a
person who decides to take charge of
their future can have a tremendous
impact on how far they get and how
powerful they end up sure so the point
is preaching personal responsibility to
people actually works but it doesn't
necessarily change than that outcome
right right right
it may be that you make yourself more
powerful in somebody else loses you know
say his name you don't know right right
so the question then is as always how do
you find the correct fraction right the
intersectional story isn't totally wrong
there
is you know there are patterns of self
reinforcement where a distribution of
power and well-being and wealth self
reinforced sure such a pattern doesn't
even need to think about race sure the
extent that things weren't really
distributed to begin with all you need
is a pattern that reinforces right the
existing distribution right that will
continue indefinitely right
so the question is how do you take the
part of the story that is legitimate
which is yeah we do have a chronic
problem right and it does require that
it be addressed on the other hand you as
an individual would be a fool to
surrender your mind as you say right to
this process right right that's the
place where you have the greatest chance
all right you know beating the odds
right and you know the mixture of those
two messages is right what I think the
universal message would be the
recognition of the collective problem
sure and the individual problem okay do
you find that is present in anything in
any story I find that it is present in
individuals and tiny groups okay tiny
groups well brings us back to Judaism it
could be argued that Judaism is the
story and I don't mean like the religion
logically I mean the basic story of
people enslaved in Egypt gone to the
promised land that basic story has been
it's no coincidence I think that that
basic story has been sort of repurposed
in different mediums and contemporary
forms because it has both the individual
and the collective element in it built
within it but perhaps that's why people
gravitate toward it or one of the
reasons why people gravitate to what it
is because it has that sort of balance
to a certain extent yeah
I like it and I you know there's a there
is a deep connection that I'm not sure
how far to go with here but there's a
way in which
if you put aside Richard Dawkins view of
the way mimetic cultural transmission
works in evolves and you accept what
some of us see which is that these
belief structures religions are in fact
meme complexes that have served
population is very proud of course they
are right almost doesn't see it as
Richard Dawkins I think at this point
but that's a very I don't want to you
know we don't have of course they are
main complexes if by meme you mean when
I think you mean by mean which are
repeatable sort of like yeah
transmittable yes there its heredity
outside of the genome and you know I
don't know if you know this but the
concept of meme is Richard Dawkins
concept yes I write that but when I met
with him in October it was clear that he
views mimetic evolution as a kind of
side light what does that mean it's a
minor fact oh rather than a thing the
east central story yeah we're human
beings and what does he think is the
central story I think it's the things
genes and you know there's a way in
which we can steal man the Dawkins point
I do think right you know I can explore
this in greater depth some rough so you
think the genes are in control sure
right they are though I don't know what
that means but it means that the genes
create a mind okay we serines can be
transmitted they are uncharged sorry
that is most unfortunate
sure but sir but the point is yes the
magic of humans is the meat right so the
complex rights if you take the meme
complex of this did your story for
example you can find it in you know it
just repeats itself in let's take
something contemporary
oh the Lion King for example right or
you know you know there's a reason why I
Bob Marley gravitated toward the picking
that story as a backdrop for music and
sort of recreating it oh absolutely
right and of course even in the black
experience how that sort of overlays on
to as a
narrative right and which is a way to
understand oneself if you can point back
to a particular this is the argument by
the way for the particular of that story
the particulars particular miss of the
Jewish story makes it such that the the
black collective in America
I don't know houses of years later can
look back at that story and take that
story and derive meaning from it and
that is if their particular story right
without that particular story it could
have there could have been another
future I don't know but but that is very
particular as opposed to universal right
it is not the that story is not the
collective story of everyone it's a very
particular story but that because of its
particular Ness it was able to be taken
and overlaid by people who also went
through slavery right so now they
understand now they can they can relate
to that
and a deeper love on a deeper level and
create you know different forms of
meaning and of course if you look at
what black I would say black people do a
gospel and music in general the gospel
in particular especially songs that were
that preceded gospel that were sung
during slavery that took the language
and the Liturgy of the Jewish story and
sort of incorporated and it into what
slaves at that time we're going through
as a means to overcome you know the
situation I think that's an example of
how something can still be particular
but still affect in a positive way the
whole of humanity oh it's absolutely
beautiful and I love the Bob Marley
example yeah now I hope I'm not gonna
get out of my depth here okay there's a
way yeah Bob Marley plays very much on
some of the Jewish part of the story
mhm very much on some of the Christian
part of the story sure and there is a
way in which Bob Marley corrects a piece
of the Christian story and I actually
that's interesting regard as malware
okay now we're to keep oppressed people
oppressed right the song
get up stand up sure right yeah most
people think great God will come from
the sky right away everything and make
everybody feel high great but if you
know what life is worth you will look
for yours on earth right you've seen the
light stand up for your rights right
this that is a that is a that does
challenge a certain aspect of it
absolutely challenges a certain aspect
of Christianity and it to me
it aleene's towards the Jewish version
it does it does because Judaism isn't so
overly fixated with afterlife exactly
excited on the present thanks Zack doing
mitzvahs now to bring in the press right
at the same time however yes I will I
will put a vote for this aspect of
Christianity the fact of the idea of the
afterlife yep within Christianity made
it possible for black people to think to
themselves while they were undergoing
oppression that there is a say it there
is a place outside of here mmm-hmm right
there is a place beyond this realm that
I am seeing and experiencing with my
physical body right it the belief in the
afterlife equips the mind or is a tool
for the mind because it makes it it
makes you able to sort of like withstand
some of the blows that are happening in
the present because what's important is
not the present what's important is the
future well in that way yeah does it not
mirror dr. King's invocation of the arc
of the moral universe being yeah right
yeah that's same sort of right and it's
inevitably going to cut right it's
inevitably going to cut it is long so
anyway to go back to the meme complex
yeah idea mm-hmm the thing that I the
thing about memes and meme complex is
that they enjoy the ability to recombine
it's very much analogous to what happens
with genes okay alright with two people
mate they bring assurance together you
get some new combination there's a way
in which Christians mm-hmm if we take a
phylogenetic view mm-hmm
of these populations the Christians are
in effect a species of Jews Jews
effectively the ancestral okay yeah a
much larger population has emerged from
it yes right it dwarfs the Jewish
population but so what I would say is
Christians are they are phylogenetically
Jewish okay modern Jews are in part
culturally Christian okay they have
actually adopted things from the New
Testament that aren't in the Old
Testament including them in their meme
complex so for example monogamy mmm
right so mm-hmm
yeah and you know you can you can sort
of say well Bob Marley is playing with
the mixture of the Chiefs yeah right
yeah I mean with the mixture of beliefs
and to a particular population
particularly oppressed population right
that needed music right just sort of
Reese crypt right they were and get them
to look past the Christian obligation
right just simply endure right right so
Bob Marley is like somebody he's like a
a meme mixer okay in order to generate a
more powerful story yeah in your sense
of it this is a natural process right it
has to happen you know it happens when
people combine ideas and they jettison
these sure opted those and they mix them
and bring them in and sure so anyway
there is a very powerful story to be
understood if we figure out how these
massive meme complexes do evolve what
way it's similar to dreams in which ways
it is dissimilar in one way it is
subservient to genes it's gonna be a
very important part of the story but in
any case if we were to start looking at
the world through that lens I believe we
would have a great deal of power to
understand patterns of history that are
otherwise just simply anomalous okay
because the because you will find a
common story or which would be
effectively Amin
right because it will it will stop being
difficult you know
if the idea is well are you Christian or
are you Jerry right right that's not a
really good correct exactly it's saying
yeah you know is that a monkey or is it
a primate yeah it's both right right
yeah you know not every primate is a
monkey but right every monkey is a
primate right to the extent that
Christianity is a very successful
successful version of unionism that's an
important fact sure it says something
about the way these two things will
interrelate and to the extent that an
ancestral population can embrace
discoveries of a descendant population
sure that work sure that working here
and didn't work where the ancestors came
from that's a that's a feature not a bug
okay begs the question how Bob Marley
then or why Bob Marley became so popular
given what we just given how you just
described what it was he was actually
doing I think you answered it earlier
okay and I think your point about the
way pop culture interfaces with these
ancient resonant threads mm-hmm but this
is basically right yes we've got lots of
people playing with they say things they
get a positive reaction sure they
explore those things further sure Bob
Marley was a particularly he was a
genius who explored a particular
quadrant that was very rich you know it
didn't abandon mm-hmm the traditions of
the past but it looked skeptically a
part of it it embraced other parts its
musically so compelling for instance
that you would know far more as a
musician for then I could tell you but
there's a way in which reggae is I don't
know what to say it's very it's very
basic it reaches some yes very tribal
yeah in the sense that it's I mean I
think a lot of music that's like African
or like the Caribbean like from the
African Diaspora is like that it has
that effect
it tends have that effect on many people
but there are such as African because
there I found that their elements of
African music that can be found in like
Irish and Scottish music as well and you
sort of saw it the mixture of those
music origins in America to create
American music anyway
but yeah there so all of these this type
of music that I'm thinking about whether
it's from Ireland or whether it's from
Ghana it's like very much reminds you of
like rootedness mm-hmm right and so I
think that's why ultimately Marley was
as popular because as he was because he
was speaking to something that was
fundamentally true and whether it
doesn't have to mean true in the in the
sense that Sam Harris means when he says
true right yep but it's a different kind
of meaning but something for whatever
reason or another fundamentally human
beings are wired to resonate with right
and are wired to respond to and perhaps
we don't know the why of that story you
know why that is what it is and why that
is how we are wired but it is in fact
how we are wired so at least it is
interesting to say the least
all right I have one final question I
don't know how to phrase it okay but
it's an idea that's been well thirty
minutes and I don't know maybe not I'm
hoping so you're a musician you play
guitar a little piano a real keyboard
but yeah keyboards and string keyboards
and string and I sing as well okay and
it's worth noting that the guitar is
originally an African instrument yes
yeah worth noting okay so here's the
rough idea okay something absolutely
magical happened when European melodic
sensibilities met African rhythmic
sensibilities that's that's overly
simplified sure let's just say in the
New World
sure jazz and all of its derivatives it
was like a magic combination sure of
things yeah and it unleashed my favorite
of these traditions might be Cuban salsa
okay which is in its own way kind of
remained pure low happy
because of the economic isolation of
Cuba geralt of the the embargo but
anyway something magic happened in the
new world as a result of what the slave
population brought and inevitably
combined with the slave holding
population those two musical traditions
was lightning in a bottle when they when
they met mm-hmm but here's the really
interesting thing those same two
traditions have met more than once okay
all right they met in the new world and
you know I don't know I call it once but
basically there was some influx of
slaves they brought musical traditions
sure it happened but it's also now
happened again mm-hmm in Africa right
now what I'm interested in is that I've
started listening to some of those
African versions of this so you know if
these were languages we would call it a
Creole okay right so Creoles two
languages they meet people who speak
these two languages speak what's called
a pidgin which is not a full language
but their children speak a Creole it was
a full language that that is composed of
the two or extreme languages but it is
neither of them sure a musical Creole is
the same thing okay but you know these
artists like Habib Cote or Jane I
encountered recently mm-hmm it's
interesting it reaches me even though
it's not you know my tradition is a
hybrid of the African sure and the
European right I say sounds from rock
and roll right that's that's where I've
that's where my ear was schooled right
but those I guess my point is every time
you take two languages you make a Creole
okay but if you take English and French
and you Creole eyes it ten times you'll
get ten different Creole therapy you
know this will be certain things that I
will be analogous but there will be
other things that are just video
syncretic based on the particulars of
the the hybridization event
mm-hmm but I think this has happened
musically and what what I'm getting at
is that there's a way in which the
African Creole between European music
and Afra
can music is a second instance of what
happened in the New World
okay and it's very interesting to listen
with a ear that arose in listening to
the American the new world version of it
it is very interesting to listen for the
African version of it because basically
it's another combination of the same two
traditions right it isn't the same
combination right and so it has some
elements that are very familiar and some
that are foreign right
and I'm wondering I've seen this pattern
are yeah well I mean there's one album
called effets that everyone should
listen to I just interviewed their
bandleader for my podcast um anybody
podcast yes the theory of Enchantment
the theory even Sam the podcast yes but
this band FA basically is based in San
Juan Puerto Rico and it combines ancient
like Aruban prayers with electronic
drums almost so it's a it's it reminds
me of what you were talking about and
it's definitely contained elements
contains elements of the old but the
combination is what makes it new the
type of combination that it is is what
makes it new right because there's the
same things but it's not combined in the
same way because things have changed
obviously so and that has created a
specific like new type of music that
I've never heard before but I don't know
if I've noticed that it's common it
could it could be that I'm not exposed
to a lot of that type of music
specifically or it could just be that I
listen to a lot of old music so I'm just
listening to a lot of older stuff that
still like speaks to me mm-hmm but I
don't know I haven't I haven't seen it
but that doesn't mean it does exist okay
cool what's the name of the album
Etha IFE IFE all right cool there are
definitely the best band I've heard in
the past probably 10 years Wow yeah
that sounds pretty good I'm definitely
going to YouTube that check it out yeah
cool all right
all right final question are you are you
hopeful am i hopeful yeah I mean I I am
hopeful because I do believe that
certain things are inevitable and I and
I know for it's not just like the sort
of of course it's long it's arduous you
know this this arc that we've been
talking about but you know what is also
consistent is the hero's arc and the
hero's journey which is a certain type
of archetypal story pattern that is
found in a lot of stories that we tell
ourselves and because it's found in so
many stories I am convinced that like
more or less that's the story that's
going to be able to empower individuals
with healthy balance for the collective
it's a story we've been telling
ourselves all along it may it may be
that we have to present it in a new way
similar to this new Creole that's
created in Africa right but it will
contain the same elements and we will
recognize the element those elements
which is precisely why we will buy the
story and it's true that the story of
like do this selfishly so you can gain
power is also a very compelling story
but it doesn't have it doesn't have
redemption there's no redemption in that
story and I think that's that's the
difference that's like the thing that
separates the boys from the men does not
have redemption in it I really like this
idea and I do think that there it's too
simple to say that the the hero
archetype story keeps being retold which
I sometimes hear people say I did not
hear you say that
okay I think there is a manner in which
the hero archetype story has to be
reinvented for each generation mm-hm
um you know that the Lord of the Rings
yeah it's great story but it's not it's
not modern sure it's not up-to-date
enough right it needed to be redone and
I hope we do find that story for our
cohort we're not of the same generation
but you and I are seeing the same piece
of history at the moment yeah I hope
that we figure out the version of that
story that causes
people to realize I don't know that we
can dance together yeah right that we're
really one people and yeah that the
future in fact depends on us getting
past the dangerous tribalism that have
led us here
yes well Haiti's a four-letter word but
the future depends on love so that's
fine for later all right
well Chloe Valerie this has been a
extreme a long one no it's been long but
anyway it would have been ashamed to cut
it short I agree
it's all very worthwhile from my
perspective thank you for coming on the
Dark Horse podcast thank you for having
me
and people can find you at theory of
Enchantment yes my website is theory of
Enchantment come check it out shoot me
an email
I'm also on Twitter so Steve Alderete
see Valerie and you can also follow
through even chef Valerie
spelled not how you might expect it it's
about VA l da ry Val dari yes so okay
excellent well this has been great thank
you all for joining us if you wish to
support my work you can do so on patreon
and stay tuned a lot more coming in the
weeks to follow
[Music]